A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Knowledge, Creativity and Freedom, Office of the Vice President, Office Files of Alison R. Bernstein FA573
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Knowledge, Creativity and Freedom, Office of the Vice President, Office Files of Alison R. Bernstein
1974-2007, bulk 1986-2007
1986-2007
Rockefeller Archive Center
Bernstein, Alison R., 1947-
Ford Foundation
FA573
7.86 Cubic Feet 6 record storage boxes
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Scope and Contents
Primarily documents meetings, events, and initiatives as well as providing subject files, working files and publications.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement
Arranged in 7 series by file type.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Aguerrebere, Joseph, 1999
Series II. DAGs/RAGs, 2000-2002
Series III. African Higher Education Initiative, 2001-2007
Series IV. Working Files, 2003-2006
Series V. Subject Files, 2001-2007
Series VI. Reports, 1974-2000
Series VII. Publications, 1979-2002
Biographical / Historical
Dr. Alison Bernstein worked at the Ford Foundation from 1983 until 2010, with a break in the early 1990s to assume the position of Associate Dean of the Faculty at Princeton University. Bernstein started as a program officer in 1983, and she was named director of Education and Culture at the Foundation in 1992. Bernstein was later promoted to vice president of the Ford Foundation's Education, Creativity and Free Expression Program, later called called Creativity and Free Expression. In 2011, Bernstein left the Foundation to become the director of the Institute for Women's Leadership at Rutgers University.
- Aguerrebere, Joseph, 1999; I
  - Program Division Leadership Meeting, 1999 (Box 1)
- DAGs/RGAs, 2000-2002; II
  - EMAC DAGs -- US Overseas by Field Office, 2000-2002 (Box 1)
  - MAC/EKR -- FY 2002 DAGs (Box 1)
  - MAC/EKR -- FY 2002 RGAs (Box 1)
  - Agendas/OVP -- FY 2002 RGAs, 2001-2002 (Box 1)
  - FY 2002 RGAs -- Overseas by Office (Box 1)
- African Higher Education Initiative, 2001-2007; III
  - Higher Education Collaboration between RF/Carnegie/McArthur/FF, 1999-2005 (Box 2)
  - African Higher Education Partnerships Presidents Meeting 1/17/03 -- Partnership for Higher Education in Africa Contracts (1/2), 2006 (Box 2)
  - African Higher Education Partnerships Presidents Meeting 1/17/03 -- Partnership for Higher Education in Africa Contracts (2/2), 2006 (Box 2)
  - African Higher Education Partnerships Presidents Meeting 1/17/03 -- Partnership for Higher Education in Africa Signed Contracts, 2006 (Box 2)
  - African Higher Education Partnerships Presidents Meeting 1/17/03 -- Africa Higher Education, 2006 (Box 2)
  - African Higher Education Partnerships Presidents Meeting 1/17/03 -- African Higher Education Meeting Materials, 2005-2006 (Box 2)
  - African Higher Education Partnerships Presidents Meeting 1/17/03 -- Farah J. Griffin, 2005 July 14 (Box 2)
  - African Higher Education Partnerships Presidents Meeting 1/17/03 -- Meeting with Leaders of African Higher Education, 2005 September 15 (Box 2)
  - African Higher Education Partnerships Presidents Meeting 1/17/03 -- Africa Education, 2005 September 16 (Box 2)
  - African Higher Education Partnerships Presidents Meeting 1/17/03 -- Nairobi Documents -- Africa Higher Education, 2005 (Box 2)
  - African Higher Education Partnerships Presidents Meeting 1/17/03 -- African Higher Education Partnerships Presidents Meeting, 2003 November 17 (Box 2)
  - Meeting of the Presidents, 2004 November 29 (Box 2)
  - Briefing Book, 2004 (Box 2)
  - Meeting of the Presidents, 2005 February 23 (Box 2)
  - African Higher Education Success Stories, 2005 July 1 (Box 2)
  - Partnership Event -- Trustee and VIP Invites, 2005 September 16 (Box 2)
  - Partnership Event, 2005 September 16 (Box 2)
  - Meeting of the Presidents, 2005 November 17 (Box 2)
  - Meeting of the Presidents, 2006 February 23 (Box 2)
  - Partnership for Higher Education: Lunch, 2005 September 16 (Box 2)
  - Africa Higher Education -- Oct 2-5, 2006 -- General, 2004 (Box 2)
  - Africa Higher Education -- Oct 2-5, 2006 -- Alison Bernstein Information Packet, 2004 (Box 2)
  - Africa Higher Education -- Oct 2-5, 2006 -- Information Pack, 2004 (Box 2)
  - Africa Higher Education -- Africa Higher Ed, 2007 April 27 (Box 2)
  - Africa Higher Education -- Meeting of the Presidents (1/2), 2007 April 27; DVD (Box 2)
  - Africa Higher Education -- Meeting of the Presidents (2/2), 2007 April 27 (Box 2)
  - Africa Higher Education -- PHEA Presidents Meeting, 2007 April 27 (Box 2)
- Working Files, 2003-2006; IV
  - Ford Foundation International Fellowships Program -- Discussion, 2001 April 16 (Box 3)
  - Ford Foundation International Fellowships Program -- Board of Directors Meeting, 2003 January 13; DVD (Box 3)
  - International Fellowships Fund Board of Directors meeting, 2003 January 13 (Box 3)
  - Appalshop -- NYC, 2003 November 10 (Box 3)
  - ITVS -- Sally Jo Fifer, 2003 December 8 (Box 3)
  - International Fellowships Program, 2003-2004 (Box 3)
  - Leaders for a Changing World -- General, 2004 (Box 3)
  - Leaders for a Changing World -- Final Evaluation Report, 2006 February (Box 3)
  - International Fellowships Fund -- General, 2004 (Box 3)
  - International Fellowships Program -- Oxaca Mexico, 2004 January 15 (Box 3)
  - International Fellowships Fund -- Board of Directors Meeting, 2004 September 13 (Box 3)
  - International Fellowships Fund -- Advisory Committee, 2004 (Box 3)
  - International Fellowships Fund -- Board of Directors Meeting, 2005 January 10 (Box 3)
  - International Fellowship Fund: Update, 2005 January (Box 3)
  - International Fellowships Fund -- Advisory Committee Meeting, 2005 March 14-15 (Box 3)
  - International Fellowships Fund -- Reception, 2005 March 15 (Box 3)
  - International Fellowships Program Fellowships, 2005 March 15 (Box 3)
  - International Fellowships Fund -- Board of Directors Meeting, 2005 May 9 (Box 3)
  - Leadership for Social Justice 8, 2005 June 12-17 (Box 3)
  - International Fellowships Program -- Washington DC, 2005 June 15 (Box 3)
  - International Fellowships Fund -- Board of Directors Meeting, 2006 January 30 (Box 3)
  - International Fellowships Fund -- Board of Directors Meeting, 2006 May 8 (Box 3)
- Subject Files, 2001-2007; V
  Arrangement
  Alphabetical.
  - Ad Hoc Consultations Briefing Book and Schedule -- Vietnam-Dioxin Materials, 2007 February 10-16 (Box 4)
  - Brazil, 2006; DVD (Box 4)
  - Committee on Indigenous Peoples -- Learning Forum, 2005 May 20 (Box 4)
  - Difficult Dialogues -- Reports, 2004 (Box 4)
  - Difficult Dialogues -- Leonard Dinnerstein -- Correspondence, 2004 (Box 4)
  - Difficult Dialogues -- Religious Pluralism, 2004 December 3 (Box 4)
  - Difficult Dialogues -- Antisemitism, 2005 January 4 (Box 4)
  - Difficult Dialogues -- Request for Proposal Meeting -- University of Miami, 2005 February 4-7 (Box 4)
  - Difficult Dialogues -- Thank You, 2005 April (Box 4)
  - Difficult Dialogues -- Difficult Dialogues, 2005 (Box 4)
  - Difficult Dialogues -- Difficult Dialogues -- Finals, 2005 (Box 4)
  - Difficult Dialogues -- Difficult Dialogues, 2006 (Box 4)
  - Difficult Dialogues -- Request for Proposals, 2005 (Box 4)
  - Difficult Dialogues -- Difficult Dialogues RGAs, 2006 (Box 4)
  - Difficult Dialogues -- News Articles, 2005 (Box 4)
  - Difficult Dialogues -- Difficult Dialogues RGAs, 2006 (Box 4)
  - Difficult Dialogues -- Difficult Dialogues Memorandum, 2005 (Box 4)
  - Difficult Dialogues -- Difficult Dialogues Conference -- Omni Hotel New Haven, 2007 January 11 (Box 4)
  - Difficult Dialogues -- Religious Grantees, 2006 October 25 (Box 4)
  - Difficult Dialogues -- Ford Foundation Workshop -- Exploring Aspects of Grantmaking in Europe, 2006 June 14-15 (Box 4)
  - Diversity Fellows -- Edgar Beckham -- Diversity Luncheon at the Ford Foundation, 2004 June 10 (Box 4)
  - Diversity Fellows -- Edgar Beckham -- Tri-National Seminar on Diversity Issues in Higher Education -- Materials, 1997 February 6 (Box 4)
  - Diversity Fellows -- Edgar Beckham -- Diversity Letter to University Presidents, 2004 July (Box 4)
  - Diversity Fellows -- Edgar Beckham -- Diversity Fellows Trustee Signature, 2005 (Box 4)
  - Dream Fund, 2004 October 19-20 (Box 4)
  - Education and Culture Teamwork Project, 1996 January-June (Box 4)
  - Exploring Europe Grantmaking Group (EEGG), 2006 (Box 4)
  - Piper Fogg Interview -- Chronicle of Higher Education, 2005 March 30 (Box 4)
  - Ford Foundation Media and Arts and Culture (MAC) Grantmaking: Historical Profile, 1951-2001 (Lynn E. Stern), 2003 (Box 4)
  - The Ford Foundation -- 10 Years in Russia, 2006 (Box 4)
  - Fund for Community Organizing, 2006 November 16-17 (Box 4)
  - Fund for Community Organizing -- Assessing Community Change -- An Evaluation of the Community Organizing Initiative, 2006 April (Box 4)
  - HIP HOP Convening, 2003 November 5 (Box 4)
  - ICPD+10 World Leader Statements, 2004 (Box 5)
  - Institute of International Education -- Scholar Rescue Fund Report, 2007 (Box 5)
  - International Fellowships Fund Program Advisory Committee, 2000-2001 (Box 5)
  - International Fellowships Fund -- Board of Directors Meeting, 2002 June 24 (Box 5)
  - International Fellowships Fund -- Board of Directors Meeting, 2003 May 12 (Box 5)
  - International Fellowships Fund -- Board of Directors Meeting, 2003 September 8 (Box 5)
  - Ford Foundation International Fellowships Program, 2001 (Box 5)
  - International Fellowships Program -- Report, 2003-2004 (Box 5)
  - International Fellowships Fund -- Board of Directors Meeting, 2004 May 10 (Box 5)
  - Steve Lawry Luncheon, 2006 June 21 (Box 5)
  - MLK Library -- Mayor Shirley Franklin, 2006 (Box 5)
  - Rutgers KCF Retreat, 2005 (Box 5)
  - Stone Soup, 2004 March 5 (Box 5)
  - Trip File -- Paris, France, 2003 March 6-7 (Box 5)
  - Vietnam Meeting, 2006 July 20 (Box 5)
  - Winston Salem Journal 2004, 2003-2005 (Box 5)
  - Workshop - The First Emperor Shanghai Workshop for Music Education, 2006 (Box 5)
  - World Trade Center Foundation, 2005 March 2 (Box 5)
- Reports, 1974-2000; VI
  - That 51 Per Cent, 1974 (Box 5)
  - That 51Per Cent... Plus, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Looking Back, Moving Ahead: A decade of school finance reform, 1980 (Box 5)
  - The Political Economy of Education, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Status Report on the Education and Culture Program, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Created Equal -- A Report on the Ford Foundation's Women's Programs, 1986 (Box 5)
  - And Gladly Teach, 1987 (Box 5)
  - The Education and Culture Program's Math and Science Program, 1988 December (Box 5)
  - Feminist Pluralism, 1987 (Box 5)
  - Ford Foundation Annual Reports -- Education and Culture, 1988-1992 (gaps) (Box 5)
  - Task Force 2000 -- Creating 21st Century Schools, 1989 October 25 (Box 5)
  - Toward a New Professorate, 1990 February 28 (Box 5)
  - Foundation Supported Commissions, 1991 July (Box 5)
  - Diversity in American Higher Education, 1992 June (Box 5)
  - The Ford Foundation and the Urban Poor in the 1950s, 1993 October 21 (Box 5)
  - Education and Culture 1994-1995 Biennium Budget and Program Paper, 1993 (Box 5)
  - History of the Ford Foundation's Programmatic Philosophies 1950-1994 -- K-12 School Reform (Box 5)
  - Anti-Delinquency, Great Cities, Gray Areas, 1987-1994 (Box 5)
  - Reflections on the Ford Foundation's Worldwide Workshop on Culture, 1995 June (Box 5)
  - Achieving Diversity in the Professoriate, 1996 (Box 5)
  - The Role of the Ford Foundation Fellowship Program for Minorities in the Production of PhDs, 1997 October (Box 5)
  - Report on Women's Studies Consultancy, 1998 February 26 (Box 5)
  - Review of Ford Foundation Grants on Language, 1999 (Box 6)
  - School Accountability, 2000 June 30 (Box 6)
  - Evaluation of 21st Century School Fund "Theory of Change", 2000 (Box 6)
  - The Impact of Challenges to Race Based Admissions and Financial Aid on Minority Fellowships, 2000 January 10 (Box 6)
  - A Review of Afro-American Studies Programs for the Ford Foundation, 2000 (Box 6)
- Publications, 1979-2002; VII
  - Ford Foundation Annual Reports, 1979-2000 (Box 6)
  - Ford Foundation Report Magazine, 1995-2003 (Box 6)
  - 40 Years: A Learning Curve -- The Ford Foundation in India 1952-1992 (Box 6)
  - Forestry for Sustainable Rural Development, 1998 (Box 6)
  - EMAC Annual Retreat, 1999 September 21-22 (Box 6)
  - Ford Foundation President's Message, 1999 (Box 6)
  - Solving the Math Problem -- Ford Foundation's Work on Reforming Middle and Secondary School Mathematics 1980-1998, 1999 (Box 6)
  - Law and Ford Foundation Grantees and the Pursuit of Justice, 2000 (Box 6)
  - (EMAC) Education, Media, Arts and Culture Retreat, 2001 (Box 6)
  - Women's Leadership, Gender and Peace, 2001 (Box 6)
  - The Ford Foundation 1952-2002 (Box 6)